Multiple Linear Regression



Understanding the Data
Reading the Data in
Multiple Regression Model
Prediction
Practice

#Importing Needed packages

import matplotlib.pyplot as plt
import pandas as pd
import pylab as pl
import numpy as np
%matplotlib inline


#Downloading Data
#To download the data, we will use !wget.


!wget -O FuelConsumption.csv https://s3-api.us-geo.objectstorage.softlayer.net/cf-courses-data/CognitiveClass/ML0101ENv3/labs/FuelConsumptionCo2.csv
Did you know? When it comes to Machine Learning, you will likely be working with large datasets. As a business, where can you host your data? IBM is offering a unique opportunity for businesses, with 10 Tb of IBM Cloud Object Storage: Sign up now for free

#Understanding the Data
#FuelConsumption.csv:
#We have downloaded a fuel consumption dataset, FuelConsumption.csv, which contains model-specific fuel consumption ratings and estimated carbon dioxide emissions for new light-duty vehicles for retail sale in Canada. Dataset source

MODELYEAR e.g. 2014
MAKE e.g. Acura
MODEL e.g. ILX
VEHICLE CLASS e.g. SUV
ENGINE SIZE e.g. 4.7
CYLINDERS e.g 6
TRANSMISSION e.g. A6
FUELTYPE e.g. z
FUEL CONSUMPTION in CITY(L/100 km) e.g. 9.9
FUEL CONSUMPTION in HWY (L/100 km) e.g. 8.9
FUEL CONSUMPTION COMB (L/100 km) e.g. 9.2
CO2 EMISSIONS (g/km) e.g. 182 --> low --> 0
Reading the data in

df = pd.read_csv("FuelConsumption.csv")
​
# take a look at the dataset
df.head()
Lets select some features that we want to use for regression.


cdf = df[['ENGINESIZE','CYLINDERS','FUELCONSUMPTION_CITY','FUELCONSUMPTION_HWY','FUELCONSUMPTION_COMB','CO2EMISSIONS']]
cdf.head(9)

Creating train and test dataset
Train/Test Split involves splitting the dataset into training and testing sets respectively, which are mutually exclusive. After which, you train with the training set and test with the testing set. This will provide a more accurate evaluation on out-of-sample accuracy because the testing dataset is not part of the dataset that have been used to train the data. It is more realistic for real world problems.

#This means that we know the outcome of each data point in this dataset, making it great to test with! And since this data has not been used to train the model, the model has no knowledge of the outcome of these data points. So, in essence, it’s truly an out-of-sample testing.


msk = np.random.rand(len(df)) < 0.8
train = cdf[msk]
test = cdf[~msk]
Train data distribution

plt.scatter(train.ENGINESIZE, train.CO2EMISSIONS,  color='blue')
plt.xlabel("Engine size")
plt.ylabel("Emission")
plt.show()
Multiple Regression Model
In reality, there are multiple variables that predict the Co2emission. When more than one independent variable is present, the process is called multiple linear regression. For example, predicting co2emission using FUELCONSUMPTION_COMB, EngineSize and Cylinders of cars. The good thing here is that Multiple linear regression is the extension of simple linear regression model.


from sklearn import linear_model
regr = linear_model.LinearRegression()
x = np.asanyarray(train[['ENGINESIZE','CYLINDERS','FUELCONSUMPTION_COMB']])
y = np.asanyarray(train[['CO2EMISSIONS']])
regr.fit (x, y)
# The coefficients
print ('Coefficients: ', regr.coef_)
As mentioned before, Coefficient and Intercept , are the parameters of the fit line. Given that it is a multiple linear regression, with 3 parameters, and knowing that the parameters are the intercept and coefficients of hyperplane, sklearn can estimate them from our data. Scikit-learn uses plain Ordinary Least Squares method to solve this problem.

Ordinary Least Squares (OLS)
OLS is a method for estimating the unknown parameters in a linear regression model. OLS chooses the parameters of a linear function of a set of explanatory variables by minimizing the sum of the squares of the differences between the target dependent variable and those predicted by the linear function. In other words, it tries to minimizes the sum of squared errors (SSE) or mean squared error (MSE) between the target variable (y) and our predicted output ( 𝑦̂  ) over all samples in the dataset.

OLS can find the best parameters using of the following methods:

- Solving the model parameters analytically using closed-form equations
- Using an optimization algorithm (Gradient Descent, Stochastic Gradient Descent, Newton’s Method, etc.)
Prediction

y_hat= regr.predict(test[['ENGINESIZE','CYLINDERS','FUELCONSUMPTION_COMB']])
x = np.asanyarray(test[['ENGINESIZE','CYLINDERS','FUELCONSUMPTION_COMB']])
y = np.asanyarray(test[['CO2EMISSIONS']])
print("Residual sum of squares: %.2f"
      % np.mean((y_hat - y) ** 2))
​
# Explained variance score: 1 is perfect prediction
print('Variance score: %.2f' % regr.score(x, y))
explained variance regression score:
If y^ is the estimated target output, y the corresponding (correct) target output, and Var is Variance, the square of the standard deviation, then the explained variance is estimated as follow:

𝚎𝚡𝚙𝚕𝚊𝚒𝚗𝚎𝚍𝚅𝚊𝚛𝚒𝚊𝚗𝚌𝚎(𝑦,𝑦^)=1−𝑉𝑎𝑟{𝑦−𝑦^ }𝑉𝑎𝑟{𝑦} 
The best possible score is 1.0, lower values are worse.
​
regr = linear_model.LinearRegression()
x = np.asanyarray(train[['ENGINESIZE','CYLINDERS','FUELCONSUMPTION_CITY','FUELCONSUMPTION_HWY']])
y = np.asanyarray(train[['CO2EMISSIONS']])
regr.fit (x, y)
print ('Coefficients: ', regr.coef_)
y_= regr.predict(test[['ENGINESIZE','CYLINDERS','FUELCONSUMPTION_CITY','FUELCONSUMPTION_HWY']])
x = np.asanyarray(test[['ENGINESIZE','CYLINDERS','FUELCONSUMPTION_CITY','FUELCONSUMPTION_HWY']])
y = np.asanyarray(test[['CO2EMISSIONS']])
print("Residual sum of squares: %.2f"% np.mean((y_ - y) ** 2))
print('Variance score: %.2f' % regr.score(x, y))
​